字幕翻译/压制：旋火
视频来源：youtu.be/ZIaDWCK2Bmk
原视频发布日期：20190810
原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
- Hi, it's me, Tim Dod, the Everyday Astronaut.
- 嗨 我是 Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
Rocket Lab just announced they plan to try and recover their Electron rockets using a parachute and a helicopter.
火箭实验室刚刚宣布 他们计划尝试使用降落伞和直升机来回收电子火箭
Yeah, seriously.
没错 认真的
Well, this concept of air recovering a rocket definitely isn't new.
空中回收火箭的概念并不新鲜
It actually goes all the way back to the Apollo era,
甚至起源于阿波罗时代
when NASA had some pretty crazy ideas themselves.
那时NASA自己就有一些疯狂的计划
And NASA wasn't too crazy for considering air recovery.
当然 NASA考虑空中回收这事儿并不算特别疯狂
I mean, after all the Air Force started successfully recovering film from spy satellites in orbit as early as 1960.
毕竟空军早在1960年就开始成功地(在空中)回收入轨的间谍卫星拍摄的胶片
But history hasn't always been so kind to parachutes on rockets,
但是使用降落伞回收火箭的历史却不是那么光彩
because despite trying on the first two Falcon 9 missions,
因为尽管前两个猎鹰9任务有进行过尝试
SpaceX failed to even get to the point where they deployed the parachutes.
SpaceX甚至没能成功部署降落伞
So why does Rocket Lab think that they're going to be able to do this?
那为什么火箭实验室认为他们能做到？
What's different about their plans?
他们的计划有什么不同？
So today, we're gonna dive into Rocket Lab's plans for reusability,
那么今天 我们要研究火箭实验室重复使用的计划
including some deep dives on the challenges they face,
包括研究一些他们会面临的挑战
including the forces and velocities.
包括力和速度
Then we'll go on to the history of air recovery
然后 我们将探讨空中回收的历史
and compare Rocket Lab's reusability plans to other space systems that utilize parachutes,
把火箭实验室的重复使用计划与其他使用降落伞的航天系统进行对比
such as the Space Shuttle SRBs,
例如航天飞机的固体助推器
the Falcon 9's attempts, SpaceX's fairings,
猎鹰9号的尝试 还有SpaceX的整流罩
and even ULA's similar plans they're calling SMART Reuse.
甚至还有ULA称之为SMART重复使用的类似计划
And with SpaceX now recovering fairings regularly with a parachute,
随着SpaceX现在通过降落伞定期回收整流罩
are parachutes just now with their rate to get all of a sudden?
难道降落伞突然变成潮流了吗？
What the heck is going on?
到底咋回事儿啊？
While we're at it,
在这儿
we're gonna talk a little bit about
我们还要讨论一下
why SpaceX doesn't try using helicopters instead of that boat to try to recover their fairings.
为什么SpaceX使用船而不是直升机来回收他们的整流罩
And best of all,
最重要的是
I got exclusive information from Rocket Lab
我从火箭实验室得到了独家的消息
and Peter Beck himself with some exciting additional details on
还有Peter Beck跟我说的 一些令人兴奋的细节
just how exactly they hoped to do this.
关于他们为什么想要这么做
By the end of this video,
在这个视频的末尾
hopefully you'll have a pretty good understanding if this wild plan is actually possible,
希望你能搞清楚这个疯狂的计划到底是可行的
or if it'll be back to the drawing board for Rocket Lab.
还是说它只是火箭实验室的PPT
Let's get started.
让我们开始吧
- [Mission Control] Three, two, one,
- [任务控制]三 二 一
("Mercury Redstone" by Everyday Astronaut)
and liftoff!
和升空
- [Neil] That's one small step for man.
- [尼尔]这是对人类的一小步
- [Mission Control] That's Houston contact for the test one.
- [任务控制]这是休斯敦和一号测试的通信
On August 6, 2019, Rocket Lab founder and CEO,
在2019年8月6日 火箭实验室的创始人和CEO
Peter Beck, made an exciting announcement
Peter Beck 宣布了一个振动人心的消息
that their company's pursuing reuse of their wildly successful Electron rocket
他们的公司正追求着非常成功的电子火箭的重复使用
at the Small Sat Conference in Utah.
在犹他州的小卫星大会上
The timing is perfect, as SpaceX just announced the same week, plans to do in-house ridesharing,
时机是完美的 这也是SpaceX宣布火箭拼车计划的同一周
which could help make the cost of launching a small satellite much cheaper.
这将使小卫星发射的成本大幅下降
Although SpaceX's announcement the day before Rocket Lab's announcement
尽管SpaceX的发布比火箭实验室的早一天
obviously didn't motivate Rocket Lab into making up a drastic reuse plan out of the blue,
这一天显然不可能让火箭实验室突然制定好重复使用的计划
it certainly made publicly clear that there's competition knocking on Rocket Lab's door.
但这显然让公众了解到火箭实验室参与到了这项竞赛当中
OK, so first things first, let's do a super quick overview of Rocket Lab's Electron rocket,
首先 我们来快速总结下火箭实验室的电子火箭
but if you want my deep dive on this rocket,
但如果你想让我深入研究这个火箭
电子火箭视频 youtu.be/C0STPK3g9c8
I've already got you covered.
这视频我已经做过了
The Electron is a two-ish,
电子差不多是2级
kind of three stage orbital small sat launcher
也有点像3级的小型卫星运载火箭
that's capable of taking 225 kilograms to lower Earth orbit.
它的近地轨道运载能力有225kg
It's 17 meters tall, 1.2 meters wide,
它高17米 宽1.2米
and the cost to launch a satellite is $5.7 million.
发射卫星费用为570万美元
It's a really unique rocket
这是一个非常独特的火箭
in the fact that it's the first rocket in the world to get to orbit using electric fuel pumps
事实上它是世界上第一个使用电动燃料泵驱动入轨的火箭
instead of a traditional turbo pump assembly that uses fuel to spin the pumps.
而不是使用传统的燃料驱动的(燃料)泵
It's also the first orbital rocket to be fully carbon composite,
这也是第一个全碳纤维复合材料的入轨级火箭
and they entirely 3D print their electric Rutherford engines.
而他们的卢瑟福发动机则完全是3D打印制造的
It's gone to orbit six times with only their first attempt not quite making it to orbit,
他们成功入轨了6次 只有他们第一次入轨的尝试失败了
and their eighth rocket is on the pad as we speak.
而现在他们的第8枚火箭已经运到发射台了
OK, now on to reusability, which I have to laugh a little bit about,
好 现在来讲重复使用能力 提到这点让我想笑
because Peter Beck has said over and over
因为Peter Beck说过好几次
that there's just not enough margin for a small launcher of this size to try to pursue reusability.
那就是这个尺寸的小运载没有足够的余量来追求可重复使用能力
采访视频 youtu.be/Nj9BncsgvuQ
Peter even talked off camera with me about reusing the Electron after I interviewed him last year.
Peter去年接受我采访 在关闭摄像机的时候跟我提到了重复使用电子火箭
To which he did have a little smirk.
对此他有点不以为然
Especially when I noted his love for helicopters.
特别是我发现他喜欢直升机
I was on to you, Peter.
Peter 我正在说你呢
So what the heck made him change his mind?
那么究竟发生了什么让他改变了主意？
I mean, he even admitted defeat at the announcement,
他甚至在发布会上承认了自己的错误
saying he'll have to eat his hat.
说他只好吃掉自己的帽子(指某事不可能发生但还是发生了)
Let's check out their plan and see what they came up with.
我们来看看他们想出了什么计划
That seems just so tantalizing.
这很吊胃口
On their upcoming 10th launch,
在他们即将到来的第十次发射
we'll see a pretty substantial block upgrade to the Electron.
我们会看到一次电子火箭的大升级
So hopefully, by the end of 2019,
但愿在2019年末
we'll see this rocket on the launchpad.
我们会看到这枚火箭在发射台上
After safe separation,
在安全分离后
the first and second stage go on their own ways,
一级和二级火箭分道扬镳
the second stage continues on to orbit,
二级继续入轨
and the first stage begins its coast up to its highest point, after which,
一级将一路到达它的最高点
it will begin falling back to Earth.
在这之后开始返回地球
At this point, we all know the drill here.
在这儿 就是我们都熟知的程序了
The rocket will continue to pick up speed as it falls back to Earth,
火箭会在返回地球的一路上增加它的速度
until it begins atmospheric re-entry.
直到它开始重返大气层
But pretty quickly, the rocket will begin experiencing serious re-entry heating.
但很快 火箭会开始经受严重的再入加热
Just like how we see the Falcon 9 start to shoot sparks
就像我们看到猎鹰9号开始喷出火花
and see plasma build up as it experiences re-entry.
看到它经历再入时的等离子体越来越多
The rocket will need to survive this re-entry without doing any kind of propulsive slowdown,
(而电子)火箭需要在不借助任何反推减速的情况下 在再入过程中生存下来
and that's pretty tricky when the plasma at the supersonic shock waves can be half the temperature of the sun.
这是相当棘手的 此时超音速等离子冲击波的温度可以达到太阳温度的一半
But Rocket Lab has a small trick up their sleeves.
但是火箭实验室有着锦囊妙计
At some point during re-entry, while still at supersonic velocities,
在超音速再入过程中的某时
the Electron will deploy a kind of supersonic de-accelerator, or a drag device known as a ballute.
电子火箭将会部署一种超音速减速器 一种拖拽设备称为气球降落伞
This helps increase the surface area of the vehicle and helps it slow down quickly.
这将提高火箭的表面面积 并很快减速
Once in the lower atmosphere and at subsonic speed,
一旦在低层大气减速到了亚音速
we'll deploy a fully steerable parafoil.
火箭将会部署一个可控的翼伞
Then believe it or not, a helicopter will actually take off from a nearby ship,
然后在这附近的一艘船上 一个直升机将会起飞
and it'll intercept it as it's falling from the sky on that parafoil.
直升机会把火箭截住 而此时火箭正借助翼伞在下降
It'll then have this little drag hook thing that will come in contact with the line,
直升机会使用这个类似抓钩的东西和绳子接触
and then will swoop it up out of the sky and take it back over to the ship.
然后降下来 把它带回到船上
And when watching this computer animation,
而看这个电脑动画的时候
you may think, uh, this seems impossible.
你可能会觉得这似乎是不可能的
Well, checkout this footage.
好吧 那么来看看这段视频
Dose this look familiar?
这看起来眼熟吗？
youtu.be/3LhBG-J7PDU
火箭实验室版www.bilibili.com/video/BV1Yp4y1C7FH
youtu.be/N3CWGDhkmbs
This footage is from PDG Aviation Services who partnered with Airborne Systems and Lockheed Martin,
这个视频是PDG航空服务和Airborne Systems还有洛克希德马丁合作出来的
who successfully demonstrated this exact technology in 2017.
在2017年成功地演示了这个技术
And I'm sure that's no coincidence since Lockheed Martin is an investor in Rocket Lab.
而且我敢肯定 这并不是巧合 因为洛克希德马丁公司是火箭实验室的投资商
It's cool that we have legit test of the system in place already.
这很不错 这个系统已经得到了测试
It makes this portion of recovery seem a lot less crazy.
让这部分的回收过程变得更加可信
Once the helicopter successfully grabs the rocket out of the air,
一旦直升机成功地在空中抓住了火箭
it'll lay it down on the back of the ship that it took off from.
直升机会把火箭放在它起飞的那艘船上
And it looks like they'll maybe employ some robots or small cranes
看起来他们也会使用一些机器人或者小型起重机
or something to softly lay it down horizontally in a transportation cradle of some kind.
或者某种能让火箭水平放置的运输支架之类的东西
And again, I know this all looks pretty crazy,
再说下 我知道这听起来很疯狂
but here's the thing.
但是
Air recovery is actually a pretty familiar thing.
空中回收其实是一个相当熟悉的东西
After all, the US Air Force begin attempting recoveries of film from space in the 1950s,
毕竟 在20世纪50年代美国空军就开始(在空中)回收从太空中再入的胶片
and they were successful as early as 1960.
而在1960年代他们就成功过
The program was called the Corona program,
这就是日冕计划
and it's honestly just plain crazy.
它也很疯狂
So back in the day, there weren't digital cameras like we know them.
那时可没有数码相机
I know.
我知道
So how the heck do you get high resolution images,
那么 你如何得到高分辨率的图像呢
especially with film, back down from space?
特别是从太空中得到的胶片？
After all, let's not forget things in orbit are literally traveling 10 times faster than most bullets,
毕竟 可别忘了入轨的物体比子弹的速度还要快10倍
and they need to survive hitting the atmosphere.
而且他们还要扛过再入大气层
This was no easy feat.
这不是一件容易的事情
What the Air Force did was house the film in a canister that was basically a small re-entry capsule.
美国空军把胶片放在一个小金属罐里 基本上就是一个返回舱
It would perform a quick deorbit burn and re-enter.
它会在进行短暂的降轨点火之后再入
Had its own heat shield that allowed it to survive re-entry.
它上面的隔热板能让它扛过再入
Once it was going slow enough, it kicked off its heat shield and deployed a parachute.
减速到一定程度之后 它会抛掉隔热板 并部署一个降落伞
Then a freaking airplane would swoop by with a giant hook on the back of it and snag it out of the sky.
然后一架尾部带着大钩子的飞机会突然飞过并把它带走
And even with a big slowed maneuvered plane,
就算是一架巨大的飞行缓慢的飞机
it actually would get about four tries before the capsule would splash down.
在返回舱溅落之前 飞机也只有四次尝试的机会
And cleverly, if they did miss it all four times,
巧妙地 如果他们错过了所有四次的尝试
the capsule had a salt plug at the base of it.
返回舱的底部有一个盐制的塞子
This gave them about two days to try to recover the capsule
他们大概有两天时间来回收返回舱
before the salt plug would be eaten away by the ocean water,
在这之后 盐制的塞子会被海水溶解掉
and it would sink to the bottom of the ocean,
然后它就会沉入海底
so that no one, especially enemy forces,
所以没有人 特别是敌军
would accidentally recover it.
会意外地恢复它
And they actually did this with a surprisingly great deal of success.
而且令人惊叹的是 他们取得了巨大的成功
With a total successful recovery rate of nearly 75%.
总的回收成功率接近75%
And maybe seeing some of this great success
也许在看到了一些这样的巨大成功之后
led to some pretty wild plans for NASA to try and air capture the first stage of a Saturn 5.
导致NASA展开了一些疯狂计划 来空中回收土星五号的一级火箭
Yeah, you heard me right, the Saturn 5,
是的 你没听错 土星五号
the largest rocket ever successfully flown,
曾经成功飞行过的最大火箭
you know that 10 meter wide, 110 meter tall rocket that took humans to the moon.
就是那个10米宽 110米高 把人类送到月球的火箭
Yeah, NASA looked into trying to snag that thing out of the sky with a helicopter
没错 NASA试图用直升机把那东西从空中钩住
that would take up an entire city block.
这个大小足以占据一整个街区
Hiller Aircraft propose building a helicopter with a rotor diameter of over 120 meters,
席勒飞机公司提议建造一种旋翼直径超过120米的直升机
that would have a useful payload of nearly 250 metric tons.
这种直升机的有效负载质量会超过250吨
The concept was to recover the first stage,
这个概念是回收一级火箭
which was still a lopping 42 meters tall and 10 meters wide.
而一级火箭虽然只是一部分 但仍有42米高10米宽
But even empty, it still weighed 130 metric tons.
空重仍高达130吨
This giant helicopter would've been powered by jet engines on the tips of the rotors.
这个巨大的直升机会被旋翼末端的喷气式发动机所驱动
Six in total to spin the tips up to nearly the speed of sound,
6个发动机将会把旋翼的末端加速到接近音速
rotating once every second.
每秒旋转一次
As nutty as the Apollo program was,
正如阿波罗计划一样疯狂
this would've been by far the most nutty thing every built.
这也会是目前为止制造出来的最疯狂的东西
And as we probably know, this program never left the drawing board,
正如我们现在所知 这个计划很可能一直都处在图纸阶段
but it's definitely not the last time we'd see recovery via parachutes.
但绝不会是最后一次使用降落伞的回收
Of course, let's not forget about the Space Shuttle,
当然 别忘了还有航天飞机
which ditched its solid rocket boosters at only about two minutes into flight.
它大概只飞行2分钟后就把固体火箭分离了
Then they did something very similar to what Rocket Lab is planning to do,
然后 接下来的事情就和火箭实验室要做的差不多
which is to coast up to their highest point,
助推器一路飞行到最高点
re-enter the atmosphere, and pull a parachute.
再入大气层 然后拉出一个降落伞
Only, as you may know,
只是 也许你知道
the SRBs were allowed to splash down due to their simple nature
因为固体火箭结构简单 所以可以溅落
some other examples of trying to recover booster with a parachute was SpaceX's attempts.
而其他试图用降落伞回收助推器的例子则是SpaceX的尝试
SpaceX originally planned to recover their Falcon 1 and their Falcon 9 with parachutes.
SpaceX原本计划用降落伞回收猎鹰1号和猎鹰9号
That's right.
没错
猎鹰9号带降落伞的的级间段
You might not know that the first two flights of the Falcon 9
你可能不知道 头两次猎鹰9号的飞行
actually had parachutes packed up in the inner stage of the rocket.
在火箭的级间段里有打包好的降落伞
After the second attempt,
在第二次尝试后
SpaceX realized they weren't even getting to the point where they could deploy the chutes,
SpaceX意识到他们甚至达不到可以部署降落伞的程度
because the boosters weren't even surviving re-entry.
因为一级火箭没能扛过再入
And therefore there really wasn't anything for the parachutes to recover.
所以没有东西留给降落伞回收了
Not to mention, they hadn't really solved how the booster would've survived the splashdown.
更何况 他们也没有解决溅落后一级火箭如何生存下来的问题
But that was probably the next step after successfully deploying the chutes.
当然 这是在降落伞成功部署以后的事情了
As we know, the program took a different turn.
正如我们所知 这个计划朝着不同的方向发展了
And another parachute recovery I wanna talk about is also with SpaceX,
而另一种我想谈到的降落伞回收方案也和SpaceX有关
because we're all of a sudden seeing them successfully recover their fairings using parachutes.
因为突然间我们发现他们使用降落伞成功回收了整流罩
As of the making of this video,
在这个视频制作之后
they've caught two fairings in a row on a boat named GO Ms. Tree,
他们已经用GO Tree女士这艘船连续回收了两个整流罩
formerly known as Mr. Steven.
之前这艘船名叫Steven先生
Now this might be confusing to some people.
现在 这件事可能把一些人搞糊涂了
How can the fairing survive re-entry without repulsively re-entering but not the booster?
为什么整流罩而不是助推器能在非反推式的再入中生存下来
Well, it mostly comes down to the surface area of the fairing and its lightweight nature.
这主要归结于整流罩的表面积(较大)以及质量较轻
And because of these things, it slows itself down in the upper atmosphere
所以它在高层大气减速(较多)
much more effectively than an air dynamic and much heavier booster.
相比与更加流线型 更重的助推器 它更容易减速
Think of it all like a piece of paper versus a pencil.
类似一张纸对比一支笔
Obviously, the piece of paper has a much greater surface area,
显然 一张纸有着更大的表面积
and the atmosphere has a much greater effect on its velocity.
而大气(减速)对它的速度有着大得多的影响
The fairing orients itself way up in the upper atmosphere using some cold gas thrusters
在高层大气 整流罩使用冷气推进器调整它的姿态
so the curvy end is down.
所以末端弯曲的那一面朝下
Then it basically serves back into the atmosphere,
之后整流罩回到了基本上是它产生作用的大气层中
bleeding off speed along the way.
一路上大量减速
Once it's in the lower atmosphere,
一旦它到了低层大气
it deploys a steerable parafoil and maintains a GPS heading and a path.
整流罩就部署一个可控的翼伞 并借助GPS 保持一定的朝向和路径
Then the ship autonomously follows that same heading,
然后船只也自动地朝向同一个位置前进
steers up underneath it and catches it.
开到它的下面并捕获它
Now that SpaceX has got two fairing house in a row,
现在SpaceX已经连续两次成功捕获了整流罩
this method is seeming more and more worthwhile.
这个方法看起来越来越有价值
It's going so well, in fact SpaceX just bought a second boat named GO Ms. Chief,
这件事如此顺利 以至于SpaceX刚买了第二艘船名叫GO Chief女士
that they're going to use to catch the other fairing half.
他们打算用这艘船捕获另外半个整流罩
And lastly, I wanna talk about United Launch Alliance's SMART Reuse system for their upcoming Vulcan rocket.
最后我想谈下联合发射联盟(ULA)准备在他们的火神火箭上面使用的SMART重复使用系统
The Vulcan rocket is the replacement to ULA's Atlas 5 and their Delta 4.
ULA准备用火神火箭替代宇宙神5和德尔塔4
It uses two methane powered BE-4 engines built by Blue Origin,
它使用两个蓝色起源制造的甲烷发动机BE-4
who will also use seven of those engines to power their New Glenn rocket.
而蓝色起源也会把七台BE-4用在自家的新格伦火箭上
The Vulcan plans to start flying in 2021,
火神预计2021年首飞
and eventually, they hope to start trying to recover the engines from the vehicle,
在这之后 他们希望开始回收火箭上的发动机
which they announced way back in 2015.
2015年就宣布了这个回收计划
Their plan is to jettison the whole thrust structure
他们的计划是要从火箭储罐上
with the engines attached from the tank of the vehicle.
抛掉整个推力结构还有发动机
They'll then deploy an inflatable heat shield
然后 他们将部署一个充气热盾
to make sure that the dense and heavy engines can survive re-entry and maintain a proper orientation.
确保密度大质量大的发动机可以扛过再入并保持一定的正确方向
Then, much like Rocket Lab's plans,
然后 就像火箭实验室的计划
they deploy a parachute once it's in the lower atmosphere,
一旦到了低层大气 就会部署降落伞
and then they'll use a helicopter to swoop it up out of the air before it splashes down.
在它溅落之前 使用直升机在空中飞过并钩取它
("Astronaut Beach House" by Everyday Astronaut)
OK, so now in order to get a sense of what Rocket Lab is attempting to do,
为了搞清楚火箭实验室到底在做啥
let's actually pull up the five different recovery methods we just talked about
我们刚才讲了五种不同的回收方法
and check out their trajectories,
并查看了他们的发展轨迹
and we'll see if we can figure out what Electron has to face.
我们来看看电子火箭要面对的是什么吧
For this, I reach out to my friend, Declan Murphy,
对于这一点 我听从了我朋友Declan Murphy的主意
who made FlightClub.io.
也就是FlightClub.io的作者
With this incredible website,
有了这个难以置信的网站
we're able to plot all of this stuff.
我们能够绘制这么多图表
And his simulations are shockingly accurate.
而他的模拟是惊人地准确
I'm so impressed by his work,
他的工作太让我钦佩了
which is why I support him on Patreon.
这就是为什么我在Patreon上支持他
And if you like his work too,
如果你也喜欢他的工作
you should consider doing the same thing.
你也可以考虑支持他
Especially if you're a rocket photographer,
特别是如果你是火箭摄影师
you can use his website to actually see exactly
你可以使用他的网站来精确地查看
where the rockets are going to be heading with your lenses and everything in frame,
在你的镜头以及其他参数影响之下 在一张照片里火箭的朝向
so you know you're not gonna miss the shot.
这样你就不会构图出问题
OK, so let's go ahead and take these five different systems and plot them out.
好吧 我们继续把这五种不同的系统画出来并对比他们
Here we have the flight profile of the Space Shuttle SRBs from STS-129, to be exact, in green.
这条绿色的是STS-129任务中 航天飞机固体助推器的飞行参数
A pretty aggressive but recoverable GTO flight profile from the first stage of the Falcon 9 in blue.
蓝色的则是猎鹰9号一级 相对激进但是可回收的GTO飞行参数
Including the fairing profile, which is in white.
白色的则是猎鹰9号(同一次发射中的)整流罩的飞行参数
Then you've got a pretty standard Electron first stage profile in red.
红色的则是电子火箭一级相对标准的飞行参数
And lastly, we've got the approximate estimate for the Vulcan rocket in yellow.
最后 黄色的则是火神火箭的大概估计
Now I wanna point out, this is just an approximate profile
需要说明的是 这只是大概的飞行参数
based on some information from Tory Bruno's reply to me on Twitter,
这个估计来自Tory Bruno(ULA的CEO)在推特上给我回复的一些信息
the Vulcan will have even longer burn times than the Atlas 5.
火神(一级)的点火时间将比宇宙神5还要长
So let's just figure an Atlas V 551 will be fairly similar to an average Vulcan GTO mission,
所以我们让宇宙神551近似等同于一个平均情况下火神GTO任务吧
(没错这是宇宙神551中正确的5的数量)
considering they share the same upper stage.
考虑到它们有着相同的上面级
And just one last final reminder here.
而最后要提醒的则是
All of these numbers are just pretty good estimations,
这些数字只是比较接近的估计
as they can vary greatly from mission to mission.
在不同任务之中差距较大
And one more note, don't forget,
还有一件事
all of these things are suborbital,
所有这些都是亚轨道的
because they still have an upper stage that will continue on into orbit.
因为这些火箭还有上面级会继续入轨
But now let's actually plot their peak velocities,
现在开始指出他们的极速
their altitudes, and their downrange distances.
他们的高度 还有他们的(靶向)水平飞行距离
Let's start off with their altitudes.
首先说明一下他们的高度
The Space Shuttle SRBs's apogee is only about 65 kilometers in altitude.
航天飞机的固体助推器的远地点仅有65km
Next, the Falcon 9's first stage rarely gets above 120 kilometers for a GTO mission.
接下来 对于一般的GTO任务 猎鹰9号的一级很少会超出120km
And then we have the fairing,
然后是整流罩
which gets a little higher at around 140 kilometers.
更高一些 差不多在140km
Followed by the Electron's first stage which gets up to around 170 kilometers.
之后是电子火箭的一级 能达到差不多170km
And lastly, we have the Vulcan's first stage,
最后 则是火神火箭的一级
which will get up to almost 250 kilometers at its apogee.
远地点高达近250km
Next, let's look at their downrange distance,
然后看看他们的水平飞行距离
or approximately how far downrange these things will end up.
或者说差不多是它们能飞到的最远距离
The Space Shuttle SRBs, again, are first,
首先是航天飞机的固体助推器
and only about 285 kilometers downrange.
大概只有285km
Followed by both the Electron and the Falcon 9 first stages, right around 620 kilometers downrange.
其次是电子火箭和猎鹰9号的一级 差不多620km
Then, the Falcon 9 fairing at around 740 kilometers.
然后 猎鹰9号的整流罩大概740km
And lastly, the Vulcan first stage will land around 3,600 kilometers downrange.
最后 火神火箭的一级大概在3600km
Last but not least, let's look at their peak velocities.
最后但同样重要的 看看它们的极速
The Space Shuttle SRBs were of course the slowest at around 5,000 kilometers an hour,
航天飞机固体助推器 当然是最慢的 在1.388km/s左右
followed by the Electron booster at around 7,500 kilometers an hour.
接下来是电子火箭一级大概2.083km/s
Then the Falcon 9 at around 8,000 kilometers an hour.
然后是猎鹰9号一级大概2.222km/s
Then the Falcon 9 fairing at around 8,500 kilometers an hour.
之后是猎鹰9号整流罩大概2.361km/s
And lastly, the Vulcan booster will reach an astonishing 20,000 kilometers an hour.
最后 火神一级将达到惊人的5.555km/s
And don't forget, the peak velocity is really an incredibly important factor here.
别忘了 这里的极速真的很重要
And that's because re-entry heat's relation to speed is cubed.
因为再入热与速度的立方成正比
So not squared, but cubed.
不是平方 是立方
That means if something is re-entering twice as fast,
这意味着再入速度增加1倍
the heat it experiences goes up eight times.
再入热量增加8倍
This is the major factor that makes re-entry so difficult
这是导致再入如此之难的主要因素
and it directly correlates to vehicles' velocities.
这与航天器的速度有着直接相关
So we have very different systems for very different reasons,
所以 构建不同的系统有着不同的原因
for each of these recovery methods.
对于不同的回收方法
For instance, the Space Shuttle SRBs didn't need any kind of propulsive re-entry or air recovery,
例如 航天飞机的固体助推器并不需要任何形式的反推式再入或者空中回收
because they were essentially just big giant metal tubes made out of 13 millimeter thick steel.
因为它们基本上只是巨大的 厚达13mm的钢管
And since they didn't get nearly as high or as fast as the others,
而且由于它们没有像别的航天器那样又高又快
it experienced less heating on re-entry,
它们再入时产生的热量很少
and because it's not a liquid-fueled rocket,
而又因为它不是液体火箭
NASA had little qualms with it splashing down.
NASA基本不担心它溅落(带来的不良影响)
That being said, it wound up being about the same cost to fish these out of the ocean than refurbish them,
话虽这么说 为了从海里把它们捞出来并修复所花费的费用
as it did just to make new ones.
基本等同于重新造一个了
OK, now let's look at the Falcon 9.
好吧 现在让我们来看看猎鹰9号
Why couldn't it survive re-entry?
为什么它不能在再入中生存下来？
Well, that's actually a very valid concern.
好吧 实际上这是一个很合理的关切
But I think another big factor wasn't surviving re-entry.
但我认为 另一个重要的原因并不是再入生存性
Perhaps they could've managed that more passively if they wanted to.
也许他们能让再入过程变得更加被动化
But SpaceX knew they had a much bigger problem lying just after re-entry.
但是SpaceX知道在再入之后还有个更大的问题等着他们
Assuming the booster survived re-entry,
假设一级火箭在再入中生存下来了
if SpaceX were to rely on parachutes,
如果SpaceX依靠降落伞(回收)
they'd be subjecting the rocket to splashing down,
他们只能让火箭溅落
which I can only imagine they really wanted to avoid.
而火箭溅落是他们真的想避免的事情
And it's not like a rocket that's the size of a 15-story building
15层楼高的火箭尺寸
that weighs over 20 metric tons empty would really be a very easy option for air recovery.
加上超过20吨的干质量 并不易于空中回收
But now with a vehicle the size of a Falcon 9,
但是像这样一个猎鹰9号的火箭的大小
SpaceX likely has a lot more leeway in their payload capacity,
SpaceX可以控制的有效载荷余量不小
and could have some more flexibility in its mission profiles,
有着更多的灵活性去调整飞行参数
or they wouldn't need every drop of performance out of the first stage.
不然他们也不会去榨干一级的每一滴性能
And they realize, they could utilize propulsive re-entry and landings effectively on most missions.
然后他们意识到 他们可以在绝大多数任务中有效地利用反推式再入和反推式着陆
Now another fun question might be why isn't SpaceX doing air recovery of their fairings?
另外一个有趣的问题可能是为什么SpaceX不对他们的整流罩进行空中回收
After all, the fairings are at much lighter weight that the Falcon 9 booster,
毕竟整流罩可比猎鹰9号的一级轻多了
and they're probably a little closer in weight to the Electron booster.
整流罩的质量比较接近电子火箭的一级
So wouldn't it be easy for them to grab a fairing out of the sky?
难道从空中钩取它不就变得简单了吗？
Well, grabbing it likely would be just as feasible,
好吧 抓取它也许同样可行
but controlling it once they catch it might not be possibly or for sure not safe.
但是抓住之后再控制它就真的变得不太安全
Don't forget, these fairings can literally fit a city bus inside them.
别忘了 这些整流罩能装下一辆城市公交车
It's so easy to forget just how enormous they are.
很容易忘记它们是如此之大
And because of their low weight and large surface area,
而且由于它们质量小 表面积大
they would essentially act like a giant sail themselves,
整流罩根本上就像一片巨帆
posing a pretty big risk to whatever aircraft would be trying to maneuver it back down to recovery vessel.
导致抓取它的飞机会受到很大风险 特别是飞机还要准备把它带到回收船的
I mean, imagine the rotor wash of a helicopter hitting that giant fairing.
想想直升机的旋翼气流吹着那个巨大的整流罩
It'd go nuts.
它会失控的
Or imagine a plane that has to go pretty quickly to fly,
或者假设是一个飞得很快的飞机(固定翼飞机)
dragging a giant sail behind it.
拖着背后的那片巨帆
It's probably just not a good idea.
这也许不是一个好主意
And besides that, the boat works.
除此之外 船做得挺不错
They've got to figure it out.
他们要搞清楚
And it's most certainly, it's cheaper to operate a boat than to have to operate a boat and a helicopter.
而更有可能是 操作一艘船比操作一艘船和一个直升机要便宜
Now it's likely that both ULA's SMART Reuse and Rocket Lab came to the same conclusion.
这么一来 ULA的SMART重复使用和火箭实验室最后可能也会得出相同的结论
They think they can safely and reliably swoop these things out of the sky before they hit the water.
他们觉得能够安全可靠地把这些东西在溅落之前迅速地抓住带走
But now one note, now because of the crazy long burn times of the Vulcan rocket,
但是注意一下 由于火神火箭(一级)的超长点火时间
the first stage will be really really far downrange,
它的水平飞行距离会变得很长
and it's going to be going really really fast.
而且(再入的时候)会变得很快
It's gonna be so fast
这是如此之快
that the Vulcan will likely see around 60 times more heating on re-entry than the Space Shuttle SRBs.
相比于航天飞机的固体助推器 火神的(发动机舱)也许会经历60倍多的再入热
Let's hope that inflatable heat shield does the job.
让我们期待充气热盾能够胜任这项工作吧
But the big takeaway here is the Electron is such a small rocket,
但我们要讨论的重点是电子是如此小的火箭
it's just the right size to be reasonable for air recovery.
对于空中回收 这种大小是合理的
I mean, sure, bigger rockets could be feasible,
可能更大的火箭是可行的
but you might actually find yourself having to also manufacture the world's largest helicopter in the mean time.
但就得同时制造世界上最大的直升机
("Astronaut Beach House" by Everyday Astronaut)
So how in the heck are they actually going to do this?
所以他们要怎么做呢
Well, there's one thing that they can't get around and that's extra weight.
有件事无法避免的 那就是增重
There will be additional weight added to the first stage of the Electron in order to make it recoverable.
电子火箭的一级会加重以获得可回收能力
But according to an email I received from Peter Beck,
但是根据我从Peter Beck那儿收到的邮件
we have some overall performance improvements to the whole rocket
整个火箭性能的总体提升
that will hopefully negate the extra mass of the stage one systems.
能帮我们抵消掉一级部分增加的质量
So luckily the first stage takes a lot less of a performance hit than a upper stage.
所以幸运地是一级对上面级的性能损失会下降不少
The general rule of thumb is the first stage
按照一般的经验
only takes about a four to one payload penalty kilogram for kilogram.
一级增重4kg 有效载荷质量减少1kg
初始速度增量 = 6250m/s
That is, if you were to add, say, 400 kilograms worth of recovery hardware to the first stage,
也就是说 如果一级增加了400kg的可回收组件
一级硬件(损失) = -34m/s
二级硬件(损失) = -147m/s
you'd only lose about 100 kilograms of usable payload capability.
你只会失去100kg左右的有效载荷质量
有效载荷惩罚系数 = 4.3:1
There for sure be extra weight for the parachute and the ballute,
这额外的质量肯定是给降落伞和减速气球的
but also the additional structures that support attaching that to the booster.
还有额外的结构用来附加这些组件
But not only has Rocket Lab had several flights to really dial in the performance of the rocket,
火箭实验室不仅有几次飞行来增加火箭的性能
they're also literally riding a technology that is prone to upgrades, the lithium ion battery.
他们也在使用一个易于升级的技术 锂离子电池
Lithium ion batteries are one of the most competitive industries in the world.
锂离子电池是世界上最具竞争力的行业之一
And best of all, Rocket Lab reaps the benefits of that competition.
最重要的是 火箭实验室会从这竞争中获得好处
Everyone is working feverishly on making a better battery
每个人都狂热地为更好的电池而工作着
since batteries are officially in absolutely everything.
因为现在电池几乎存在于所有东西里面
From where I'm sitting right now in this room alone,
从我现在正坐着的这个房间里
I can count at least five devices which all run on lithium ion batteries.
我可以指出至少5个设备都在锂离子电池上运行着
And I'm not even counting the dozens of camera batteries I have for various cameras.
而且我还没有计算我用的好几个相机所用的几十个相机电池
And Rocket Lab has mentioned there's massive upgrades coming to their Electron,
而火箭实验室已经提到他们的电子会有很大的更新
and it might be safe to assume they unlocked a little extra potential via battery upgrades
保守估计他们会通过升级电池的方式获得一点额外的性能
and additional tuning.
还有其他的调整
But that's yet to be confirmed.
但是 这尚未得到证实
Another fun thing to remember is due to their electric turbo pumps,
另一个有趣的事是 由于他们的电动涡轮泵
Electron can actually run to tank depletion.
电子可以把储罐里的燃料耗光
That's something a turbo pump engine can't really do safely.
而这是(燃料)涡轮泵的发动机不能安全地做到的
This means Rocket Lab can safely push the first stage all the way to MECO,
这意味着火箭实验室可以让一级火箭安全地飞行到一级火箭发动机关闭
and assuming the re-entry system holds up,
并假设再入系统能应付接下来的事情
they'll have a really promising recovery.
他们的重复使用能力将会很有希望
But here's something that really shocks me.
但是这里有件事让我非常震惊
Apparently they will not have any additional thermal protection systems than what's already on board,
显然 他们不会往火箭上安装任何额外的热防护系统
because according to Peter Beck,
因为根据Peter Beck
they'll use the standard systems they already have on board
他们会使用他们在火箭上已有的标配的系统
as they have a good experience of how it behaves in a heat flow.
因为他们对于这套系统在热流下的表现已经有不错的经验
At the base of the stage one,
在一级的底座上
there's already a chunky heat shield and flex boots
已经有了厚实的隔热板和柔性材料
to deal with the base flow heating from the engines.
来处理发动机的基流加热
Multiple engines create some recirculating flow regimes,
多引擎制造了一些回流区域
and they already have to deal with that anyway.
无论如何他们也必须处理这个问题
But they're also going to have to add some type of control systems
但是他们也不得不增加了一些控制系统
to make sure the stage maintains a proper and controlled orientation throughout re-entry.
在再入过程中 为了让一级保持适当且可控的方向
This might be some cold gas thrusters or even some small aero surfaces.
这可能是一些冷气体推进器 甚至一些空气动力学表面
Peter Beck didn't comment on how exactly they'll control it,
Peter Beck没有说明他们精确控制火箭的方法
but he did say there will be some control systems
但是他说了会有一些的控制系统
because they have a narrow corridor to make it work.
因为他们有一个狭窄的通道来让它工作
I assume that means they'll have a very precise re-entry trajectory
我认为这是指火箭会有非常精确的再入轨迹
and perfect angle of attack that seems to be conducive for a successful re-entry.
以及一个适合成功再入的完美攻角
But he did mention they'll have some supersonic decell devices to scrub velocity as best we can.
但他确实提到火箭上会安装超音速减速装置来更好地减速
So we know they have that ballute,
那么我们知道他们有减速气球
but I'm also thinking
但我也在想
they might have some other tricks up their sleeves to scrub off velocity at supersonic speed,
他们可能还会有些别的锦囊妙计来减少超音速段的速度
maybe even some air brakes at the inner stage, or maybe near the base as well.
也许是一些靠近级间段或者基座的减速板之类的东西
I'm not gonna read too much into their computer animation,
我不会太过相信他们的电脑动画
but I can't help but think the shiny bits on the inner stage
但我不禁想象那些级间段上的小亮片
and near the bottom look quite a bit different than their production inner stages
这些小亮片靠近(二级)底部 和他们的量产版级间段不太一样
and their thrust section.
还有火箭的推力舱部分的
If Kerbal Space Program has taught me anything,
坎巴拉太空计划告诉我
air brakes can really help scrub off a lot of speed,
减速板真的可以减掉很多速度
and they can also help maintain orientation.
并且有助于保持方向
But for my own personal speculation,
但是就我个人猜测
I definitely think surviving re-entry without any kind of repulsive burn
我肯定地认为 不需要任何反推并扛下再入
is going to be really impressive and very challenging.
将会让人印象深刻并且非常具有挑战性的
Now, I'm certainly not going to doubt that they've run the numbers,
现在 我当然不会怀疑 他们已经模拟过的数字
and feel quite confident enough in their system to survive.
以及他们对自己的系统能生存下来这件事所拥有的相当的信心
I'm just saying that it's going to be very very difficult.
我只是说 这会是非常非常困难的
I asked Peter why he thought the Electron will survive when other vehicles have failed to do so.
我问过Peter 为什么他觉得电子会生存下来而其他火箭却不能
And Peter said, "Our vehicle is very different.
Peter说 我们的火箭很不同
"The mass versus drag of the stage is different,
质量与阻力的比较是不同的
"the stiffness, the materials and the size.
刚度 材料和尺寸
"We may end up in the same place as previous efforts,
我们也许会和之前(其他火箭)的努力一样失败
"but while we see a feasible path we will go after it."
但只要有可能的话还是要试试
Now you might be asking, why don't they just do a propulsive entry?
但你可能会问 为什么他们不进行反推式再入
Really, the Electron is already absolutely pushing the limits on its payload capacity,
说真的 电子火箭的运载能力已经达到了极限
and they're running the tanks to depletion already,
而且像他们的储罐的燃料都是一滴不剩了
to just barely get those 225 kilograms into orbit.
只能勉强将225kg送入轨道
That's not a lot of payload capacity in the first place
首先来讲 这并不算很多有效载荷的能力
and Rocket Lab has already been really clever,
而火箭实验室已经很机智了
like ditching batteries and using carbon fiber tanks to just eke into orbit to begin with.
像是一开始就采取了抛弃电池 以及使用碳纤维储罐的方法 只是努力为了入轨
So now that they've added additional kit for recovery,
所以现在他们增加了额外套件来回收使用
they most certainly won't have even a drop of fuel for use with propulsive re-entry.
毫无疑问地说 他们给反推式再入留的燃料 一滴都没有了
As Peter Beck said in the announcement,
正如Peter Beck在发布会中表示
if we start adding margin for propulsive entry,
如果我们开始给反推式再入添加余量
and especially propulsive landing,
特别是反推式着陆
they'll quickly get into medium sized launch vehicle.
电子会迅速变成一个中型运载火箭
And this vehicle's sole purpose is
而电子火箭的唯一目的只是
to have as many dedicated launches for small sats as physically possible.
为小型卫星提供尽可能多的发射
And seeing how clever Rocket Lab has been to date,
到今天为止 看到如此机智的火箭实验室
I have a lot of faith in their engineering.
我对他们的设计工作产生了很大的信心
They don't tend to announce stuff prematurely,
他们不会过早地宣布某项东西
and I'm guessing they're pretty confident
我猜他们非常有信心
that this would be more successful than it might seem on paper.
这会是比图纸上更成功的项目
After all, they've actually gathered data from the last two launches.
毕竟 他们已经从过去的两次发射中收集了数据
And this upcoming mission number eight will have basically a black box named Brutus
而即将到来的第8次任务会有一个叫做Brutus的黑匣子
that they're going to recover that will record all 15, 000 channels of data in really high fidelity
他们会用这个东西高精度地记录下所有15000多种数据
to further compare that to their models and make sure they're accurate with real life.
和他们的模型进行进一步比较来保证准确性
But of course, the big takeaway here,
但当然 关键是
is even if they recover it and reuse the booster once,
即使他们只重复使用了一次一级火箭
they'll essentially double their output of potential launches,
根本上 他们也会把发射能力提升一倍
and eventually they might be able to bring the cost down even more.
并最终降低更多的发射成本
But I do have to point out one funny thing.
但我要指出一个有趣的事情
When SpaceX wasn't using parachutes for booster recovery,
当SpaceX没有使用降落伞来回收他们的一级火箭的时候
everyone asks, why aren't they using parachutes?
每个人都问 为什么他们不使用降落伞？
And now that the Electron's going to use parachutes,
而现在 电子会使用降落伞
everyone's asking, why don't they do propulsive re-entry?
每个人都在问 为什么不搞反推式再入？
I mean, there's different systems for different vehicles.
不同的火箭有着不同的系统
So what do you think about this?
所以 你怎么看？
Do you think the Electron will actually survive the wall?
Do you think they'll nail it on their first try?
Do you think they'll have to resort to propulsive re-entry?
Let me know your thoughts and questions in the comments below.
And let me know if there's any other questions you have about Rocket Lab recovery of rockets
or just space flight in general.
I've got tons and tons and tons more videos coming out,
I'm cranking them out as quickly as possible,
while also having to travel a lot like to see Starhopper and other launches and stuff,
so stay tuned, there's plenty of content coming.
And of course, I couldn't be doing all of this stuff without the support of my Patreon supporters.
They literally helped me script and research and fact check my videos,
make sure I'm not missing anything obvious.
I couldn't be doing any of this stuff without you guys.
But also, they're helping get better and better gears so I can get better shots of say, Starhopper,
or better launch coverage, better live streams.
I'm just trying to always upgrade things and make things better and better and better,
and that's all thanks to my Patreon supporters.
So consider becoming a Patreon member.
If you wanna join our exclusive discord
where you can talk rockets with people all day long
but also get your voice and questions into video scripts while I work on them,
or you can join our exclusive subreddit and also have access to exclusive live streams,
head on over to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
Thank you guys.
And while you're online, definitely checkout my new web store for shirts like this,
awesome pointy end up, flamey end down shirt.
I do runs of shirts now,
so if you want a shirt like this,
better get on it right now
because it just might not be there the next time you click on my web store.
You can also find things like grid fin not-a-coaster,
hats, mugs, lots of awesome stuff.
This store is always expanding, and there's always really cool new designs so check back often.
That's everydayastronaut.com/shop.
And while you're there,
click the music tab where you'll find links to my music that I use in all my videos,
or you can listen to it on iTunes or Spotify or wherever you listen to music.
You can add your favorite song to playlist.
Let me know if you do that.
Thanks, everybody, that's gonna do it for me.
I'm Tim Dodd, The Everyday Astronaut,
bringing space down to Earth for everyday people.
(chill music)